hi my name is james and this is a
cardano starter kit
thanks for checking it out the name of
this starter kit is how to talk about
cardano with your friends and family
and if you're thinking wow that's a
pretty presumptuous title
you're exactly right i want to get
something clear
i'm not an expert on this i'm on this
journey too and i want to figure out how
to get better at this
and if i do this starter kit right
you're going to have your own ideas at
the end of it for how you want to talk
about cardano
for how you want to address different
problems than the ones
i want to address okay we're on a
journey together
i really just want to kind of help get
conversations going
and then get out of the way now i happen
to be a teacher
we all have our own domains of expertise
mine is education and so what i want to
do to start this
starter kit is is share a few education
terms with you if you're not a teacher
maybe you don't think about things in
these terms
but i'm hoping that by throwing these
ideas out there
these might prompt some line of thinking
in your mind
and then you can pursue that so i'm
going to share these terms
don't worry too much about remembering
what the words are
i just want to get some ideas out there
so that we can then use them
as we move through this starter kit if
you find any of these
ideas particularly useful i'm providing
some links
for following up but you can also join
our conversation in the gimbal labs
discord
if you want to continue these
conversations ask new questions
ask for further resources and so on
so let's get going project-based
learning is something that we're really
big on at gimbal labs and at workshop
maybe and it's just based on this idea
that people learn
best by doing things
similar to project-based learning is
problem-based
learning we learn best when we have a
chance to figure things out
for ourselves pbl
is an acronym that's a really convenient
catch-all
for both of these terms because they're
connected
when we work on projects whether it's a
home improvement
project or a business project
anything we might want to accomplish out
in the world
we run into problems this is what
software development is all about right
we run into problems that we then have
to figure out new things
and that's how we develop expertise so
there's always this give and take
between the project i want to complete
the problems that emerge and how i learn
from both of those things
so when i use the acronym pbl i'm kind
of talking about
both of these things at the same time
now
whether we're talking about students or
just grown-ups in the real world trying
to accomplish real things
pbl gives us the opportunity to practice
collaboration
and exec executive functioning okay
executive functioning is just planning
and execution how do you set priorities
how do you make plans what do you need
to do to get the job done
and of course uh to solve most great
problems
you need a team you need to be able to
collaborate with people
teachers are always paying attention to
formative assessment this is not like
taking the sats or a big exam at the end
of the year
formative assessment happens all the
time and the point is
never to call students out on what they
do or don't know
it's for teachers to find out what
students know
so that teachers can help their students
take the next
step the teacher's responsibility then
is to provide
scaffolding based on what i know about
these learners
how can i help them understand what
their next few steps might be
i'm going to provide scaffolding to help
people along their journey of course
this doesn't happen all at once
but if we work hard at it and if we
iterate between formative assessment and
scaffolding
what we're going to eventually do is
provide people with more
agency and that's really my number one
goal as a teacher
anytime i teach i judge the lesson to be
successful
if people go away from it having more
ability to make their own decisions
more ability to define what their next
steps are
ideas that they're really excited to
follow through
on that's what learning is all about
so wrapped up in this is this
distinction between intrinsic and
extrinsic motivation right grades are
extrinsic motivators kind of like the
token value of cardano if you think
about it
right extrinsic motivation these these
these carrots and sticks
out in the world versus intrinsic
motivation
which is the feeling that oh i can't
resist
doing the next thing i want to see this
project through
i want to solve this problem because it
matters to me
and finally one more distinction between
teaching and learning i touched on this
a little bit
but the focus for all teachers has to be
how much are people learning not how
smart do i sound
not how many of my ideas can i throw out
there to the world
but how much are people really
understanding
and this is an ongoing thing in teaching
if you walk into any school
you're going to see teachers on opposite
ends and everywhere in between of this
continuum
between thinking teaching is about them
standing up and delivering content
and students actually understanding
things i've had a lot of good arguments
about this over the years but i come
down pretty strongly on the end
that it's not about me it's about how
much
other people can understand you can let
me know if it's working for this starter
kit okay i encourage your participation
so to summarize teaching is only
effective
if it leads to learning and as teachers
our role
is to think about the people that we're
trying to connect with
and find the right projects find the
right problems
find the right metaphors and find the
right stories to tell
so we can help people take the next step
on their journey
understand the next thing that they
didn't understand before
so let's apply this to cardano
over the last few months i've really
started to recognize
that preparing for a conversation with
my friends or with my family
is similar to how i plan to teach a
lesson about high school algebra
okay and so let's think about how a few
of these things apply
to planning for conversations about
cardano
first of all planning and conversations
are iterative it's not like you go from
planning then you have a conversation
then it's done
right any conversation is going to raise
new questions for you
it's going to help you recognize things
that you wish you were better at
explaining
so you're gonna have a chance to
practice that okay
it's really important to choose content
selectively there are so many
opportunities there's so many articles
blog posts
podcasts videos out there where people
talk about blockchain and cardano
don't just fill up on this content
make sure you have a chance to digest
what you're consuming
make time to think and reflect on the
ideas
that you learn and while going back to
this idea of executive functioning right
don't just watch everything you don't
have to keep up on everything
choose carefully what's relevant to you
to the people you're trying to connect
with our community is growing
right trying to keep up on every podcast
is really hard
and i'm not going to name the e there's
there's there's no way to judge which
podcasts are better than the others
because
there's no objective measure of that it
just depends on
who you're trying to talk to and what
you're trying
to accomplish okay but do be selective
whatever you select
do be selective and then make sure you
have time
to think through what you're what you're
ingesting what you're consuming from a
media perspective
now conversations help if you've never
gone to a cardano blockchain meetup
i really recommend going on meetup.com
i'll leave a link to it
and finding a cardano blockchain meetup
that's helpful to you join discord and
telegram channels
try ideas on reddit to see how they go
this is all part and parcel with
practicing and you're going to discover
the ways
that make the most sense to you about
how you're going to
communicate because at the end of the
day the little things we do
all add up i am a firm believer that
small actions
over time lead to greater results than
just grand speculation
is it fun to talk about what cardano's
going to do over the next few decades
absolutely i can daydream about that all
day and i can have really high spirited
conversations
inside the cardano community about that
but if we really want to accomplish
those things
it's not about just having those big
picture conversations
it's about doing what we can do today
to move the ball incrementally further
towards that the other metaphor right
it's a marathon
not a sprint we're not gonna just flip
the lights on one day
gogan's gonna come out right we're
learning about that
right now right that doesn't that's not
the end of the story that's just the
beginning and we all have work to do
on a daily basis one more metaphor
i love the metaphor of drops in the
bucket okay so i'm just listing
different ways you can think about it
here
again you might have a different way
that you like to think about it
that's the most important thing i'm just
throwing a few ideas out there
so here's your task for part one of this
starter kit
i want you to balance content with
reflection
watch or listen to any podcast you want
i'll make some suggestions
um later in this starter kit but don't
follow me just
whatever is relevant to you to your
goals
listen to a podcast about that and then
walk away put away the earbuds put away
your computer
whether it's uh you know cooking dinner
or
doing some chores going for a walk or
staring out the window
whatever step away and spend some time
contemplating metaphors or stories
that will help you explain that idea
then practice and iterate
go have conversations go see how those
metaphors land
and see if they work out okay finally
make sure to keep your goals in mind one
of mine is increased
agency i want more people to be able to
do more things
to be able to make their visions come to
reality
for another way to think about goals and
why this matters
let's take a look at what josh was
saying a couple weeks ago on the afrofin
lab podcast check it out like you're
understanding right now because i
believe you're going to go back and do
some more research
and trust me you start talking to your
friend about this thing so that's how it
starts right each one reach one right
so you need to go back and people need
to start
hearing and learning about this in uh
you know the topic for i mean part of
our motto is
make this crypto nonsense make sense
people need to start making this
crypto nonsense make sense to their
friends and that is the beginning of the
revolution and
adoption of blockchain technology and
also that is the first step that needs
to happen
before we can gradually uh
subliminally collect power from these
power grabbers
yes josh you see this is why you're a
great teacher
you see you have this big grand vision
for the problems we're gonna solve
what's the problem
centralization power how centralized
power can corrupt
people okay we all want to undo that we
all want to push back against
that but how well you named it we got to
take our first
step we have to have conversations with
our friends
we have to get the word out there and
it's slow work but we can help people
understand this one of the things that
helps people gain understanding like
i've already mentioned
is metaphors and stories now using
metaphors takes
practice and that's why again
conversations and planning are
iterative let's take a listen to sydney
from that same episode of the podcast
using a metaphor that he leans on quite
often
you know what joshua said is um
you you i don't know i can't say what
people on this
call know and don't know i'm not sure
who's an auto mechanic here and knows
how an engine works
um but clearly i think that everyone
on the call has driven a car before um
so you don't need to know how the engine
works
in order to get in and turn the key and
use the
brake and the gas pedals can you tell
that sydney has had a chance to practice
using this metaphor of engines in
automobiles
and how it applies to the inner workings
of blockchain
okay in that particular conversation he
was applying it
to questions that we had about mass
adoption
right but that metaphor could also work
in a one-on-one conversation with a
newcomer to cardano
and when you practice using metaphors
when you see how they fall
then you have more and more experience
and you can apply them
with more nuance to any conversation
that you hit on all right so now i'm
going to show me being kind of awkward
with a metaphor this was something that
i thought of for the first time
and i probably wouldn't say it the same
way check it out
i just got this image as you were
speaking of like a tide
just sort of like you know and like
people who are like in power like
standing in front of the tide like oh no
this isn't going to happen but they're
like
literally just like a wave just
because it's it's coming i feel like
we're in a time
and a place globally right now where
it's like
people are i think people
i think there's a lot of like a lot of
feeling of
this this sense of you know you're
you're you're a government
you're meant to be here for us and if
you're not here for us then
you know we need to be here for
ourselves and i
you know that's uh that's one of the
things that hooks me when it comes to
blockchain and like this whole idea of
decentralizing it and making it about
what are the needs that we have what the
problems that we have
like putting tools in people's hands
that's it add that to the to the
metaphor right we're trying to hand out
as many dingy boats and scuba gear and
all the things so that
so that all of us can be safe in that
wave right
it's happening but we need we need
people to understand that it's coming
yikes well i mean aziza's metaphor was
great this tidal wave coming over
all of us changing the world right and
you could extend that one if you want to
and i got so excited about it that i
jumped in with dingy boats and scuba
gear i
you know i don't know if i would say it
the same way as that again
right but that's the whole point when we
have conversations
we have a chance to practice the way we
say things
to practice the way things resonate and
you know i probably certainly wouldn't
say it the same way as
that again but i do need to go for a
walk
and think about well what are the
metaphors
how how are we helping people
navigate this wave of of new things
that's happening
now the only way to do that is through
conversations
and we're going to cover that in the
next part of this starter kit
one of the things i've learned in my
teaching career
is that the more broadly i prepare for a
lesson
the more able i am during that lesson to
really engage with people if i'm not
prepared i might just have a quick
script
to read and want to get through the
points that i want to say
but if i'm really prepared if i've done
my research
and practiced thinking about things
then i'm able to be fully present
with the people that i'm trying to help
learn something
okay a great teacher of mine
helped me understand that gentleness
comes from
strength and i've always really
appreciated that lesson
the stronger and more prepared i am
the gentler i'm able to be and speaking
of metaphors this metaphor applies to
both
physical strength being gentle with
heavy delicate objects right
and it also applies to human
relationships
so when we come to conversations
about cardano i think it helps to think
of them as
problem-based conversations
jaime gossip a famous educator he's
worked at
google and i'll link to a video
that i got this quote from he asks
these three questions what problem do
you want to solve
how do you want to solve that problem
and
what do you need to learn to solve that
problem and he shows
how personal these questions are
not only the question about the problem
we want to solve
but what can i do how do i want to
contribute
that's a very subjective question and
everybody's going to have a different
answer to it that's kind of the beauty
of decentralization
we all have a chance to
and then once you get people to talk
about the problems they want to solve
now we can start asking them okay how
can i help you how can i help you learn
what you need to know in order to do
that
now we've been collecting videos from
the community
about how to talk about cardano and i
want to share
one of my favorite clips from steve
aldrich
i'm going to let you see steve drop the
mic and then how he continues on because
i think it's a great way
uh to to kind of frame
why we think about problem and project
based learning
and what i mean by problem-based
conversations
so here's steve what problem does
cardano solve
what problem do you have in the latest
catalyst funding round we had 126
proposals which are all solving for
different problems
look blockchain or more specifically
cardano
is not a solution looking for a problem
nor is it a silver bullet
for all the problems of the world the
fact remains that
financial and governance systems across
the globe are in one way or another
broken
or at least in need of a good cleaning
up if we can
solve for the financial or identity
or governance issues in places where
these are a problem
then we have a successful project
if that then grows outward to solve
other problems
which maybe we can't even comprehend
today
well that's just groovy steve thank you
for that
and for everybody out there looking to
start conversations
that's really all you have to say what
problem do you have
now what i really like about what steve
shares there is how he continues on
to talk about how solving one set of
problems
opens up the door to solve more problems
this idea of incremental growth and
iteration
once we build habits of solving problems
together
once we practice talking about them then
we can address
even bigger problems some of which like
steve says
we haven't even imagined yet
so think back to some of that teaching
terminology i shared with you earlier
how can you treat conversations as
formative assessments
and based on what you learned from
people
how can you scaffold for your friends
and your family
how to help them learn the next thing
how well are you bringing people into
these conversations
is your focus really on helping people
learn
or do you just want to tell people how
great cardano is
all right all of us that's what our
community is for
come on anytime we could talk about how
much we love this project and
what we think it's going to do but when
it comes to talking about
cardano with your friends and family
please focus on learning
please focus on what people understand
so far
and how you're going to help them
understand what's next
we're not in charge because we're not
here just to
talk about what we want to talk about we
got to meet people where they're at
again remember this is iterative work
and it's not about you digesting all
this information that's out there
it's about how well you're prepared
to help people understand things so
this task is easy go have a conversation
and while you're having that
conversation think about what problems
people are naming
think about what metaphors might help
and maybe try using some of the ones
you've brainstormed
and as you reflect on the conversation
you'll think of new ways that you might
need to develop for explaining things
what questions came up and then
if you want to come reflect uh with with
the rest of us in discord
you'll see a link in in the materials
accompanying
this video come pop into discord
share questions that stump to you or you
found particularly interesting
share metaphors that you're proud of
using uh
and if you you know if you put your foot
in your mouth and you want to talk about
that too
we'd love to hear that i do it all the
time i'm probably doing it in this video
um but this is our practice right this
is how we learn and grow together
now optionally for this part i was
really moved um
by frederick greygards i hope i'm saying
his name right um the new
cardano foundation ceo i listened to a
30-minute interview of him on the crypto
valley podcast
and i was really impressed i really
admired
the way he was framing questions about
cardano adoption
from a problem-based standpoint and i
would really recommend
i was talking before about choosing
quality content
i would definitely recommend this as
really high quality content
really interesting uh to a hear that
cardano foundation is in
is in good hands uh as far as what i'm
hearing there
um but that he's got such a great grasp
on approaching these conversations from
a problem-based
perspective all right so next we're
gonna spend a few minutes going out into
the real world
and getting some ada into people's hands
hey everybody james here i'm from
workshop navy and we're filming a
starter kit
here on the corner of franklin street
in worcester massachusetts this is my
buddy adam
adam created the workshop maybe logo
and i'm going to use my urroy wallet to
pay him for it
right now adam you got your oil
installed oh absolutely man yes when did
you download it uh a couple days ago all
right so you got a
is it empty zero data no ada yet all
right we're going to pay adam we're
going to get them into the ada ecosystem
uh using ada so i'm going to open up my
euro wallet
i'm going to get my send screen open got
a qr code
nice i'm going to scan that here we go
scan type in the amount
type in my spending password
and go all right i hope this works
thanks james you bet now did it show up
yet
it might take a couple seconds here
there it is i got it all right awesome
um how does it feel to be holding ada in
your hands i'm stoked about it
this is so exciting all right
so yo all we want to do is encourage
people hey think about
opportunities to use this in your
day-to-day life now we got
adam on board here actually your name is
so much like ada
it is interesting okay we got ada adam
in the house we got ryan behind the the
screen here
ryan's got these these really cool ada
coins he just printed one for me on a
on a 3d printer so lots of exciting
stuff happening around here
adam thanks for coming out tonight no
problem man and uh we'll talk to
everybody soon
all right so in terms of real world use
just sending a little bit of ada back
and forth between wallets
is about the extent of what most people
can do
right now okay that's all right
there's a lot more functionality coming
out
the middle of next year gogin is going
to be fully released
we're going to be able to use it in the
coming months
as parts of it go online
we want to have chances to play with it
to see what we can do with it
and that's why cardano starter kits
exist
listen i really don't want to be the
face and the voice of cardano starter
kits
i love doing this i love sharing my own
perspective
but i'm really hoping if i if i do this
right
other people are going to want to
contribute too and that means you
if if you find this question of how
local use will contribute to the
adoption of cardano
please be in touch i know this isn't the
whole story
there's really important work going on
the enterprise level
there's really incredible work being
done around
oracle pools and decentralized
identities
and all of that is so important
it's ground breaking
alongside that let's also address these
questions of local adoption
all right if you want to get involved
there's a discord link
to accompany this starter kit where you
can come talk about
the ideas in this starter kit your own
experiences with implementation
but you can also start to participate in
some of the bigger conversations we're
having
we would love to have you there all
right
there's one more part of this starter
kit part four
i'm going to release it in a separate
video you'll see the links in the
documentation here
where we dive into marlow a little bit
and there's another call to action there
with a project you can do
um it's really exciting the vision
of the iohk team around marlow
i was just watching the october
development update
earlier today and just to see
that team talking about how this is a
tool
they want to put in everybody's hands
that's what we're here for that's what
gets me up in the morning and i
really i'm so thrilled to try to
contribute to that work
all right invite you to do the same
the action step for part three go out in
your community
help somebody get hands-on with cardano
okay
it's challenging uh to buy ada right now
okay so like i did i i
had adam design a logo for me and i
asked him hey can i pay you an ada
and he was fine with that so i did now
he's got some ada in his wallet
he now he can feel what it's like and
maybe eventually he'll purchase his own
maybe he'll use the ada i gave him to
stake it and he'll find out what that's
what that's like right maybe he'll pay
somebody else
this is how we drive adoption right we
just start
getting the the idea out there and
people start to say
ah okay i see right there's gonna be a
lot more ways
to get hands-on with cardano in the
years to come
for now let's jump in
so to close out we're going to go back
to this question about having
problem-based conversations
i'm going to let sydney take us home in
this story he tells
about a conversation he was having with
his brother so thank you so much for
spending this time with me today
make sure to check out part four if
you're interested in learning more about
marlow
and i'll see you soon take care i mean i
don't know how these things will happen
i do believe that blockchain will have a
hand in solving these problems
um and i was having a conversation just
before our call today
with my brother who is a um
a police officer for the the memphis
police police department
and his wife who uh manages um
uh nurses for one of the hospitals here
in memphis and we had this deep
conversation
about um how how do we help people
because in the memphis area um there's a
there's a lot of
um there's a lot of things that that
occur
that um uh you know that that
that are hard to deal with a lot of you
know lack of resources a lot of um
violence a lot a lot of those types of
things and i was asking so how do
how do we fix those problems and i was
trying to pull that out of them
because i know um
without a doubt that blockchain will
facilitate
those solutions so whatever they were
what they were telling me about the
problem
i know that we can we can apply their
solutions
on a blockchain network that will
meet each person individually where they
are
and help to resolve these huge problems
that we've been talking about fixing for
for centuries now